Princeton Ethiopic Manuscripts, late 1600s-1900s: Finding Aid C0776
Manuscripts Division
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 46: Miracles of Mary (Tä'ammərä Maryam), late 17th century; 46; 166 folios 3 cols., 27 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. One wooden board covered in stamped leather, stitched and open spine, lower board missing. Cloth on inside cover. 
  - One Hundred and Eighteenth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 140v-141r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared in her icon when Ga'əfär (Jafar), the king of the Muslims, ordered Christians and Jews to wear black not white.
  - One Hundred and Nineteenth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 141r-142v. (Unitid 46)
    How the wood from the building of the Church at Enədoləs became a tree every year on the feast day of the Virgin Mary.
  - One Hundred and Twentieth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 142v-144v. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary recovered the wood from the church of Dabrä Qusəqam and how she punished and then healed the person who stole the wood.
  - One Hundred and Twenty-First Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 144v-145v. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary helped the monk who fell into sin.
  - One Hundred and Twenty-Second Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 145v-146r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary saved the painter when he fell from the scaffold (repeated?).
  - One Hundred and Twenty-Third Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 146r-147v. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary told Timotewos the Archbishop and son of Deyosəqoros about the flight of the Holy Family into Egypt.
  - One Hundred and Twenty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 147v-152v. (Unitid 46)
    How the keeper of the church from the district of Sə'id denied Christ and the Virgin Mary and how the Virgin Mary saved him when she spoke through her icon.
  - One Hundred and Twenty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 152v-153v. (Unitid 46)
    How the Christian monk who converted to the Jewish faith.
  - One Hundred and Twenty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 153v-154r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary helped Abba Samu'el of Qäləmon when he was captured by Bärəbär.
  - One Hundred and Twenty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 154r-155r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary raised from the dead the priest named Enədrəyos of Qäləmon.
  - One Hundred and Twenty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 155rv. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary gave garments to Bishop Niqola who was of Mira.
  - One Hundred and Twenty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 155v-157r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary punished the widow who gave to other churches a gift that belonged to the church of Virgin Mary.
  - One Hundred and Thirtieth Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 157r-159v. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary protected the church of Sändäfa called Däbrä Mətmaq from the hand of Al Ašərif, the King of Egypt.
  - One Hundred and Thirty-First Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 159v-160r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary told the Holy Family to flee to Egypt and reside at Däbrä Qusəqam.
  - One Hundred and Thirty-Second Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 160v-162r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary killed a certain Jew when he insulted Jesus and the Virgin Mary.
  - One Hundred and Thirty-Second Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 162r-164r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary saved two monks on their journey to their monasteries.
  - One Hundred and Thirty-Second Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 164r-166r. (Unitid 46)
  - One Hundred and Thirty-Second Miracle of Mary, late 17th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 166r. (Unitid 46)
    How the Virgin Mary blinded those Muslims who plundered the church called Däbrä Adwäya (incomplete).
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 47: Miracles of Mary (Tä'ammərä Maryam), Miracles of Jesus (Tä'ammərä Iyassus), late 18th century; 47; 111 folios 2 cols., 17 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Two miniatures. No case. Wooden boards covered in stamped leather, stitched and leather-covered spine. Fols. 1r, 111rv: Blank 21.5 x 26 cm (Unitid 47)
  Illustration: Fol. 2v: Drawing of Virgin Mary and the Christ Child with angels with drawn swords and broad decorative border.
  Illustration: Fol. 110v: Miniature of Joachim and Hannah with large orange border and with notes above their heads: "How Joachim prayed" and "How Saint Hannah prayed".
  Fol. 1v: Note of the sale of the manuscript in faint ballpoint pen in another hand. States the date is Tər 26, 1928 EC. Sellers, the buyer, and the witnesses names included.
  Fols. 3r, 13r, 15r, passim: Original owner noted at the beginning of each miracle, in the intercession: "Virgin Mary be with Wäldä Maryam."
  Owner: Wäldä Maryam.
  References: See references listed in manuscript no. 8 and 41.
  - Beginning of a Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 2r. (Unitid 47)
    One column, probably as a pen trial.
  - Miracles of Mary Interspersed With Miracles of Jesus, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 3r-110r. (Unitid 47)
    - Introductory Rite from Mu'alləqa, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 3r-6r. (Unitid 47)
    - Prayer to the Virgin Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 6r-7v. (Unitid 47)
    - Extended Version of Introductory Rite from Mu'alləqa, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 7v-12v. (Unitid 47)
    - First Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 13r-15r. (Unitid 47)
    - Second Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 15r-19r. (Unitid 47)
      How the Virgin Mary accepted the Book of her Miracles compiled by Saint Hildefonsus [Däqsəyos], Bishop of Toledo (Budge, Mary 1; Strelcyn 15, 1.1; Bland 1; Romances, Cleopatra 7).
    - Third Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 19r-20r. (Unitid 47)
    - First Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 20r-22r. (Unitid 47)
      How the midwife Salome glorified Jesus (not in Budge; Strelcyn 16, 3).
    - Fourth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 22r-23v. (Unitid 47)
    - Fifth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 23v-25v. (Unitid 47)
    - Sixth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 25v-28r. (Unitid 47)
    - Second Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 28r-30v. (Unitid 47)
      How Jesus entered the temple [Presentation of Jesus in the Temple] (Strelcyn 16, 5).
    - Seventh Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 30v-32v. (Unitid 47)
    - Eighth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 32v-35v. (Unitid 47)
    - Ninth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 35v-37v. (Unitid 47)
    - Third Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 37v-39r. (Unitid 47)
      How Jesus recovered the stolen cattle of a man called Tətəməna in Nazareth (Strelcyn 16, 8).
    - Tenth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 39r-42r. (Unitid 47)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared to a Roman youth called Zacharias who crowned her icon with roses and how she saved him from bandits because they saw roses flowing from his mouth when he recited her sälam and how they converted and became monks (Budge, Mary, 10)
    - Eleventh Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 42r-43v. (Unitid 47)
    - Twelfth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 43v-45vr. (Unitid 47)
    - Fourth Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 45v-47r. (Unitid 47)
      How Jesus recovered the stolen calf in Palestine after commanding it to speak.
    - Thirteenth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 47r-48v. (Unitid 47)
      How the Virgin Mary moved the Monastery of Ekona (Budge, Mary, 13).
    - Fourteenth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 48v-50v. (Unitid 47)
    - Fifteenth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 50v-52r. (Unitid 47)
    - Fifth Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 52r-54r. (Unitid 47)
      How the lion glorified Jesus before Joseph the Carpenter (Strelcyn 16, 11).
    - Sixteenth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 54r-56r. (Unitid 47)
      How the Virgin Mary restored the sight of Elizabeth, a blind girl, with her breath and milk (Budge, Mary, 16).
    - Seventeenth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 56r-58r. (Unitid 47)
    - Eighteenth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 58r-59r. (Unitid 47)
      How the Virgin Mary delivered the soul of the scribe who was writing the book of her miracles (Budge, Mary, 18).
    - Sixth Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 59r-60v. (Unitid 47)
    - Nineteenth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 60v-62r. (Unitid 47)
    - Twentieth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 62r-63v. (Unitid 47)
    - Twenty-First Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 63v-66r. (Unitid 47)
    - Seventh Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 66r-67v. (Unitid 47)
      How Jesus healed the blind (Strelcyn 16, ?).
    - Twenty-Second Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 67v-69v. (Unitid 47)
    - Twenty-Third Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 69v-71r. (Unitid 47)
      How the Virgin Mary healed a person called Märqorəwos of his leprosy (Budge, Mary, 23).
    - Twenty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 71r-73r. (Unitid 47)
    - Eighth Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 73r-74v. (Unitid 47)
      How Jesus raised from the dead the son of the widow of Nain (Strelcyn 16.18, 32.16.30).
    - Twenty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 74v-79r. (Unitid 47)
      How the Virgin Mary aided in the delivery of a child to an abbess before the bishop came to enquire into the matter (Budge, Mary, 25; Bland 24 [but much shorter] also in Vincent de Beauvais (from 1264)).
    - Twenty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 79r-80v. (Unitid 47)
      THow the Virgin Mary received the soul of Barok, a dissolute man (Budge, Mary, 26).
    - Twenty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 80v-81r. (Unitid 47)
    - Ninth Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 81r-85r. (Unitid 47)
      How Jesus was baptized by John the Baptist (Strelcyn 16).
    - Twenty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 85r-86v. (Unitid 47)
      How the Virgin Mary helped a monk to escape the monastery of Qäləmon when persecuted by other monks (Budge, Mary, 28).
    - Twenty-Ninth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 86v-88v. (Unitid 47)
      How the Virgin Mary saved the soul of the cannibal of Qəmər (Budge, Mary, 29).
    - Thirtieth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 88v-89v. (Unitid 47)
    - Tenth Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 89v-91v. (Unitid 47)
      How the Jewish leader begged Pilate to burn the body of Jesus (Strelcyn 16).
    - Thirty-First Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 91v-92v. (Unitid 47)
    - Thirty-Second Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 92v-93r. (Unitid 47)
    - Thirty-Third Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 93r-94r. (Unitid 47)
    - Eleventh Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 94r-96r. (Unitid 47)
      How Jesus rose from the dead (Strelcyn 16, 37).
    - Thirty-Fourth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 96r-97v. (Unitid 47)
      How the Archangel Gabriel took the body of the Virgin Mary.
    - Thirty-Fifth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 97v-99r. (Unitid 47)
      the Virgin Mary appeared in the monastery of Däbərä Mətəmaq.
    - Synaxarium Entry for the Sixteenth Day of Yäkatit, on the Assumption of the Virgin Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 99r-102v. (Unitid 47)
    - Thirty-Sixth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 102v-103v. (Unitid 47)
    - Thirty-Seventh Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 103v-106v. (Unitid 47)
    - Twelfth Miracle of Jesus, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 106v-107v. (Unitid 47)
      How Jesus recovered the fish stolen from a fisherman (Strelcyn 16, 9).
    - Thirty-Eighth Miracle of Mary, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 107v-110r. (Unitid 47)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 48: Missal (Mäśəhäfä Qədasse), 1889; 48; 125 folios 2 cols. 24 lines [fols. 5r-41r], 19 lines [fols. 42r-124r]. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. With musical notation. Two miniatures. No case. Wooden boards; broken upper board, repaired with string. Leather-covered spine. Fol. 1rv: Part of spine binding. The number "2165" appears upside down in Arabic numerals. Fols. 2v, 3v-4r, 124v-125v, 41v: Blank. 19.5 x 26 cm (Unitid 48)
  Illustration: Fol. 2r: Outline of decorative häräg
  Illustrations: Fols. 5r, 8r, 10v, 17r, 20r, 34v, 35r, 45r, 49r, 59r, 69r, 78r, 85r, 90r, 91v, 101r, 108r, 112r, 116r, 118v: Decorative härägs.
  Illustration: Fol. 4v: Outline in black ink of angel with drawn sword. With decorative border
  Illustration: Fol. 84v: Outline of priest with hand cross (not original to the text).
  Fol. 3r: A note made in 1896 EC listing the witnesses who can confirm the paternity of a daughter (in another hand).
  Fols. 9v, 16v, 36v: In the supplications for the king, the king mentioned is King Mənilək [r. 1889-1913].
  Fols. 20v, 45r, 49r, 59r, 78r, 91v, 114v, 116r: Some owners' names mentioned: Kəfəlä Maryam and his father Gäbrä Maryam.
  Fols. 24r: Another owner's name is mentioned: Kəfəlä Səyon.
  Fols. 24v, 25v, 33v, 35r, 39r: Metropolitan bishops' names mentioned: Abba Sälama [r. 1841-1867] and Abba Pətəros [r. 1876-1889].
  Fols. 49v: Metropolitan bishop's name mentioned: Abba Matewos [r. 1889-1926].
  Date of text (1889 AD) is estimated based on several items in the text, including mention of the bishops' names and the king's name. Abba Sälama [r. 1841-1867] died in 1867. Abba Pətəros [r. 1876-1889] was replaced by Abba Matewos [r. 1889-1926] in 1889, who was in Ethiopia since 1881. The text includes a prayer for the recently deceased Abba Sälama on fol. 25v, so it cannot have been made before 1867. It probably was not made after 1889 because the text mentions the current metropolitan, Abba Pətəros. The text also mentions King Mənilək [r. 1889-1913] who only overlaps with the current metropolitan, Abba Pətəros, for one year, 1889 AD. The latest date actually mentioned in the manuscript, in another hand, is 1896 EC [1904 AD].
  Owners: Kəfəlä Maryam, Gäbrä Maryam, Kəfəlä Səyon.
  References: Marcos Daoud and H. E. Blatta Marsie Hazen, The Liturgy of the Ethiopian Church (Cairo, Egyptian Book Press, 1959); Ernest Hammerschmidt, Studies in Ethiopic Anaphoras, 2nd rev. ed., (Stuttgart 1987). Catalogs: EMIP 27, 46, 59, 72; Streclyn ?
  - Office Prayer, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 5r-17r. (Unitid 48)
    - Prayer of the Covenant, Sälotä Kidan, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 5r-8r. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplications, Mästäbqä', 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 8r-11v. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for the Sick, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 8rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for the Traveler, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 8v. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for Rainfall, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 8v. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for Farming (Lit. "Fruits of the Earth"), 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 8v-9r. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for Rivers, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 9rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for the King, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 9v. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for the Departed, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 9v-10r. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for the Catechumens, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 10r. (Unitid 48)
    - Supplication for the Peace of the Church, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 10rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany, Liton, for the Days of the Week, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 10v-14v. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for the Miracle of Mary, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 10v. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Mary, Lä-Nəgətä Kulənä, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 10v. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Monday, Enzä Nä'äkwäto, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 11rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Tuesday, Səməkä Həyaw, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 11v. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Wednesday, Lätərus Egzi'o, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 11v-12r. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Thursday, Kämä Tadhənänä, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 12rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Friday, Täzäkkär Egzi'o, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 12v. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Saturday, Sobä 'äkko Egzi'abəher, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 12v-13r. (Unitid 48)
      Fol. 12v: There is an error, the scribe replaced the litany for Saturday with the litany for Holy Saturday.
    - Litany for Wednesday, Lätərus Egzi'o, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 11v-12r. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Sunday, Lä-'amälakä Məhərätt, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 13r. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for the Dead (Lit. the Sleeping), 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 13rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for the Dead, Egəzi'ä Həyawan, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 13v-14r. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for the Dead, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 14r. (Unitid 48)
    - Litany for Vespers, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 14rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Prayer of Supplication, Nägś, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 14v-17r. (Unitid 48)
  - Ordinary of the Mass and Anaphoras, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 17r-122v. (Unitid 48)
    - Ordinary of the Mass, Sərə`ata Qədasse, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 17r-34v. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of the Apostles, Qədasse Häwarəyat, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 35r-44v. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Our Lord, Qədasse Egəzi', 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 45r-49r. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Mary Attributed to Cyriacus of Bəhənsa, Qədasse Maryam Gwäsə'a, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 49r-58v. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of John, Son of Thunder, Qədasse Yohannəs Wäldä Nägwädgwad, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 59r-69r. (Unitid 48)
      Fol. 59r: The scribe made a mistake, titling the Anaphora of John Son of Thunder, the Anaphora of John Chrysostom
    - Anaphora of the 318 Orthodox Fathers, Qädase Zä-Śäläsətu Mə'ət, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 69r-78r. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Epiphanius, Qədasse Epifanəyos Abiy, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 78r-84v. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Gregory, Brother of Basil, Qədasse Gorgorəyos'əhəwä Basələyos, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 85r-89v. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Dioscorus, Qədasse Diyosəqoros Emqədəmä 'aläm, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 90r-91v:. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Athanasius, Qədasse Atənatewos Asämə' Läkəmu, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 91v-101r. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Basil, Qədasse Basələyos, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 101r-108r. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of John Chrysostom, Qədasse Yohannəs Afä Wärəq Nahu Nəzenu, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 108r-112r. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Jacob of Serugh, Qədasse Zä-śərug, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 112r-116r. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Gregory [the Wonder Worker], Qədasse Gorgorəyos, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 116r-118v. (Unitid 48)
    - Anaphora of Cyril, Qədasse Qerəlos, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 118v-122v. (Unitid 48)
      Fol. 118r: The scribe made a mistake, titling the Anaphora of John Chrysostom as the Anaphora of Cyril.
    - Hymns Which Are Parts of Each of the Preceding Anaphoras, Śärawitä, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 123rv. (Unitid 48)
    - Seal of the Bread of the Host, With Indications of Which Portion Goes to the Priest and Deacons, 1889; multiple folios; Located on folio 124r. (Unitid 48)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 49: Psalter. Dawit, 1922; 49; 166 folios 1 col. [3r-147v], 22 lines; 2 cols [148r-166r], 22 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Six miniatures. Leather case. Plain wooden boards, stitched and open spine. 18.5 x 24.5 cm (Unitid 49)
  Illustration: Fol. 1v: Miniature of a mustached man in purple and red. Probably the owner.
  Fols. 119v: Missing lines inserted in upper margin.
  Owner: Ejəgu Nəguśe.
  Scribe: Aläqa Ayəna'aläm.
  - Psalms, 1922; multiple folios; Located on folio 3r-128r. (Unitid 49)
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments, 1922; multiple folios; Located on folio 128v-141r. (Unitid 49)
  - Song of Songs (With Musical Notations), 1922; multiple folios; Located on folio 141r-147v. (Unitid 49)
  - Praise of Mary (Wəddase Maryam), 1922; multiple folios; Located on folio 149r-161r. (Unitid 49)
    - Monday, 1922; multiple folios; Located on folio 149r-150r. (Unitid 49)
    - Tuesday, 1922; multiple folios; Located on folio 150r-152r. (Unitid 49)
    - Wednesday, 1922; multiple folios; Located on folio 152r-154r. (Unitid 49)
    - Thursday, 1922; multiple folios; Located on folio 154r-156v. (Unitid 49)
    - Friday, 1922; multiple folios; Located on folio 156v-158r. (Unitid 49)
    - Saturday, 1922; multiple folios; Located on folio 158r-159v. (Unitid 49)
    - Sunday, 1922; multiple folios; Located on folio 159v-161r. (Unitid 49)
  - Gate of Light, 1922; multiple folios; Located on folio 161r-166r. (Unitid 49)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 50: Unidentified, early 18th century; 50; 1; Two wooden boards covered in red stamped leather with detailed tooling. No manuscript or binding; 33.5 x 33.8 cm (Unitid 50)